Willam Fonds Provenance
Papers of William Fonds Provenance
1917 1955
Cupcake Corners Historical Society Center for the Study of the Giants of Archivy
Provenance, William Fonds 1897-1956
3 boxes
1.2 cubic feet
50 diaries
Mss 2 A
Correspondence, diaries,and writings of an archival theorist and author documenting his experiences in World War I, his literary endeavors, and his ideas on modern archival theory, especially regarding the centrality of the fonds.
Information about the collection.
Biography of William Provenance
Archivist and author William Fonds Provenance was born at Last Chance, Nevada to Fred and Mary Jones Provenance on January 4, 1897. Little is know of his early life prior to serving in World War I as an ambulance driver. After graduating from Freen College in 1924 with a degree in cryptogamic biology, he first followed a career in commercial horticulture and later worked as an itinerant archivist. Provenance also had a lifelong interest in creative writing, producing both novels and poetry. He died at Frostbite Falls, Minnesota on March 15, 1956.
Scope and Contents of the Papers
The collection consists of diaries, correspondence, manuscripts, and miscellaneous materials documenting the literary and archival career of William Fonds Provenance.
The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, principally with his mother, other archivists and writers. His diaries describe his experiences as an ambulance driver in France during World Was I in vivid detail. Major correspondents represented in the collection include Ernest Hemingway, Ernst Posner, and Provenance's long-time companion Ima Gusdorf.
Arrangement of the Papers
The papers are arranged into two series:
Correspondence, 1919-1955.
Diaries, 1917-1918
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the Cupcake Corners Historical Society. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Persons
Gusdorf, Ima May; Hemingway, Ernest 1899-1961; Posner, Ernst; Ball, Joseph Hurst 1905-; Bowles, Chester, 1901-; McCarthy, Eugene Joseph, 1916-; Shipstead, Henrik, 1881-1960; Youngdahl, Oscar Ferdinand 1893-1946; Provenance, William F. William Fonds 1897-1956
Topics:
Cataloging of archival materials; United States History World War, 1914-1918 Personal narratives, American; Cooperative marketing of farm produce Minnesota
Document Types
Novels; Diaries
Related Records
The papers of Ima Gusdorf are located in the Freen University archives.
The Historical Society has several other collections that include materials on archival theory.
Restrictions on Access
Access to the correspondence between Provenance and Ernest Hemingway is restricted until 2025.
Acquisition Information
Acquired as a gift from Ima Gusdorf, December 17, 1952
Other Formats
This collection is also available on microfilm.
Appraisal
Portions of this collection were heavily weeded.
Custodial History
This collection was in the possession of Ima Gusdorf until it was transfered to the archives
File Plan
An index to the collection was created by Ms. Gusdof. It is appended to the finding aid.
Additions to the Collection
No additions are anticipated.
Legal Status:
No known laws restrict access to the use of this colleciton.
Other Information
There is no further information about Provenance's teenage years which probably were as odd as you might imagine.
Location of Originals
The self-published version of Provenance's work, The Tao of Archives, is in the Frostbite Falls Public Library.
Other Finding Aids
Ms. Gusdorf's preliminary finding aid is located in the accession file.
Technical Issues
Much of the collection is fragile and must be handled with gloves.
Separated Materials
Photographs have been transferred to the Iconography Department for storage.
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Correspondence, 1919 1955; 5 folders
  Incoming letters and copies of outgoing correspondence with family, business associates, and prominent archivists and writers. Letters are arranged alphabetically by the writer's or recipient's name.
  - A-F (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gusdorf, Ima, 1942-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Access to some this file is restricted due to the personal nature of the contents.
  - H-P (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Schellenberg, Theodore, Schellenberg describes his evolving understanding of historical manuscripts. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - T-Z (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Diaries, 1917-1918; 32 v. (4 folders)
  Daily accounts of Provenance's experiences during his military service in France during World War I, primarily documenting the daily activities of camp life, weather, battles, and operations of the army medical service. Also contains detailed and graphic accounts of his own work as an ambulance driver.
  - 1917 (Box 3)
    - January-March (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Some of the materials are highly fragile.
      Extensive information on the winter weather in France and the shortage of good wine and cigarettes.
    - April-December, April is the cruelest month. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - More varied stuff, June 30; Discussion of whether or not April showers bring May flowers.
  - 1918 (Box 3)
    - January (Box 3, Folder 4)
      This file considers a wide range of topics including herbacious borders and German wines.
    - February- June (Box 3, Folder 5)